{
  "status": "success",
  "data": [
    {
      "question": "Who was the first Indian to raise the demand for a constitution-making committee for India in 1934?",
      "answer": "C) M. N. Roy",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) Motilal Nehru",
        "B) Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "C) M. N. Roy",
        "D) Gopalakrishna Gokhale"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In which conference did the Indian National Congress formally demand a constitution-making committee for India?",
      "answer": "A) Lucknow Conference of 1936",
      "moreDetails": "In 1935, the Congress formally raised the demand for a constitution-making committee for India. This demand was introduced at the 1936 Lucknow session of the Congress and reiterated at the Faizapur Conference in 1937.",
      "arr": [
        "A) Lucknow Conference of 1936",
        "B) 1934 Bombay Conference",
        "C) Haripura Conference of 1938",
        "D) Tripura Conference of 1939"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who presided over the Lucknow Conference of 1936, when the demand for a constitution-making committee was formally introduced?",
      "answer": "B) Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "moreDetails": "Jawaharlal Nehru presided over the Lucknow Conference in 1936 and the subsequent Faizpur Conference in 1937.",
      "arr": [
        "A) Maulana Abdul Kalam Azad",
        "B) Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "C) Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
        "D) Nelly Sengupta"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which Viceroy announced the August Offer in 1940, accepting the Congressâ€™s demand for a constitution-making committee?",
      "answer": "A) Lord Linlithgow",
      "moreDetails": "Congress rejected Linlithgow's August Offer, which proposed support for the British during World War II.",
      "arr": [
        "A) Lord Linlithgow",
        "B) Lord Wavell",
        "C) Lord Mountbatten",
        "D) Lord Chelmsford"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following led to the formation of the Constituent Assembly of India?",
      "answer": "C) Cabinet Mission",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) Cripps Mission",
        "B) Mountbatten Plan",
        "C) Cabinet Mission",
        "D) Wavell Plan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When did the Cabinet Mission visit India?",
      "answer": "A) March 24, 1946",
      "moreDetails": "Lord Wavell was the Viceroy of India when the Cabinet Mission visited.",
      "arr": [
        "A) March 24, 1946",
        "B) April 3, 1947",
        "C) August 3, 1947",
        "D) March 21, 1946"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the head of the Cabinet Mission?",
      "answer": "C) Pethick Lawrence",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) Stafford Cripps",
        "B) A. V. Alexander",
        "C) Pethick Lawrence",
        "D) Clement Attlee"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following was NOT a member of the Cabinet Mission?",
      "answer": "D) Clement Attlee",
      "moreDetails": "Clement Attlee was the British PM who appointed the Cabinet Mission.",
      "arr": [
        "A) Stafford Cripps",
        "B) A. V. Alexander",
        "C) Pethick Lawrence",
        "D) Clement Attlee"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When was the election of members to the Indian Constitution Drafting Committee held?",
      "answer": "D) August 1946",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) February 1946",
        "B) March 1946",
        "C) June 1946",
        "D) August 1946"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding the election of members to the Constitution-making Committee? \n 1) Direct election by adult suffrage.\n 2) Members from different political parties.\n 3) Nominated members from British Indian princely states.\n 4) Election of members in proportion to population.",
      "answer": "D) 2, 3, and 4 only",
      "moreDetails": "The Constituent Assembly consists of members from various British provinces and princely states.\r\n\r\nWhile members from the provinces of British India were elected from the respective provincial legislatures by the method of Single Transferable Vote, members from the princely states were nominated by the heads of the respective states.",
      "arr": [
        "A) 1, 2, 3, and 4",
        "B) 1, 2, and 3 only",
        "C) 1, 2, and 4 only",
        "D) 2, 3, and 4 only"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the number of members of the Constituent Assembly?\n",
      "answer": "All of these",
      "moreDetails": "15 members of the Constituent Assembly were independent members",
      "arr": [
        "The Constituent Assembly had elected members and nominated members",
        "There were 208 people who were elected as Congress representatives in the Constituent Assembly",
        "Muslim League representatives were 73 members in the Constituent Assembly",
        "All of these"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the correct statement regarding the Constitution-making Committee?\n\n1) Cabinet constituted it on the recommendation of the Mission.\n2) Election of members was done using the Proportional Representation System, providing communal representation.\n3) The seats allocated to each province were divided proportionally by population into Muslims, Sikhs, and General.\n4) Members were allotted to each province/princely state in the ratio of approximately 1:1,000,000 (1:10 lakh).",
      "answer": "All are correct",
      "moreDetails": "Cabinet constituted it on Mission's recommendation; Election used Proportional Representation System with communal representation; Seats divided by population for Muslims, Sikhs, and General; Members allocated in 1:1,000,000 ratio",
      "arr": ["1, 2 only", "2, 3 only", "1, 2, 4 only", "All are correct"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Total members of the Constituent Assembly?",
      "answer": "389",
      "moreDetails": "Out of 389 total members: 292 from British provinces, 4 from British Chief Commissioner Provinces, 93 from princely states",
      "arr": ["299", "389", "296", "93"]
    },
    {
      "question": "How many total members from princely states were there?",
      "answer": "93",
      "moreDetails": "Out of a total of 389 members, 292 were from various British provinces, 4 from the British Chief Commissioner Provinces (Delhi, Ajmer, Coorg, and British Balochistan), and 93 from princely states.",
      "arr": ["299", "389", "296", "93"]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Indian Constitution Drafting Committee was formed on which date?",
      "answer": "December 6, 1946",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "December 6, 1946",
        "December 9, 1946",
        "December 11, 1946",
        "December 13, 1946"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first meeting of the Indian Constitution-Making Committee was held on?",
      "answer": "December 9, 1946",
      "moreDetails": "The first meeting was held in Delhi",
      "arr": [
        "December 6, 1946",
        "December 9, 1946",
        "December 11, 1946",
        "December 13, 1946"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The number of people who attended the first meeting?",
      "answer": "207",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["211", "207", "389", "299"]
    },
    {
      "question": "The total number of members after the partition of India?",
      "answer": "299",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["299", "389", "296", "93"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who addressed the first meeting on 9th December 1946?",
      "answer": "J. B. Kripalani",
      "moreDetails": "When the Constitution-Making Committee was formed and India gained independence, J. B. Kripalani was the president of the Indian National Congress.",
      "arr": [
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Dr. Satchidananda Sinha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who presided over the first meeting?",
      "answer": "Dr. Satchidananda Sinha",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Dr. Satchidananda Sinha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was nominated as temporary Vice President on December 9, 1946?",
      "answer": "Frank Anthony",
      "moreDetails": "Nominated by Dr. Satchidananda Sinha",
      "arr": [
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
        "H. C. Mukherjee",
        "Frank Anthony",
        "H. P. Modi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was elected as Permanent Chairman on December 11, 1946?",
      "answer": "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
      "moreDetails": "In the same conference, H. C. Mukherjee and B. N. Rao were also selected as Legal Advisers to the Constitution-Making Committee.",
      "arr": [
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Dr. Satchidananda Sinha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Apart from H.C. Mukherjee, who was appointed as the second Vice-Chairman of the Constitution-Making Committee?",
      "answer": "V.T. Krishnamachari",
      "moreDetails": "V.T. Krishnamachari is one of the main originators of the Community Development Program (1952), regarded as the first step in Panchayat Raj administration.",
      "arr": [
        "Frank Anthony",
        "V.T. Krishnamachari",
        "D.P. Khetan",
        "T.T. Krishnamachari"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who introduced the Objective Resolution on December 13, 1946?",
      "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "moreDetails": "The Preamble codifies basic ideas of this Resolution",
      "arr": [
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Dr. Satchidananda Sinha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When was the Objective Resolution passed?",
      "answer": "January 22, 1947",
      "moreDetails": "Jawaharlal Nehru presented the Objective Resolution outlining the goals of the Indian Constitution, and the Preamble codifies the basic ideas of this Resolution.",
      "arr": [
        "January 22, 1947",
        "February 22, 1947",
        "March 13, 1947",
        "February 21, 1947"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When was the Drafting Committee formed?",
      "answer": "August 29, 1947",
      "moreDetails": "The Drafting Committee was formed to shape the Indian Constitution, and its primary responsibility was to draft the Constitution.",
      "arr": [
        "August 26, 1946",
        "August 16, 1947",
        "August 29, 1947",
        "August 15, 1947"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the head of the Drafting Committee?",
      "answer": "B. R. Ambedkar",
      "moreDetails": "Played a key role in formation of Indian Constitution",
      "arr": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "B. R. Ambedkar",
        "Gopalaswamy Iyengar",
        "Alladi Krishnaswamy Iyer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "How many members were in the Drafting Committee including Chairman?",
      "answer": "7",
      "moreDetails": "B. R. Ambedkar was the Chairman",
      "arr": ["4", "5", "7", "9"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which members were not present till the end of Drafting Committee?\n\n1) Gopalaswamy Iyengar\r\n2) B. L. Mitter\r\n3) Alladi Krishnaswamy Iyer\r\n4) D. P. Khetan",
      "answer": "2,4",
      "moreDetails": "Dr. B. R. Ambedkar, Alladi Krishnaswamy Iyer, N. Gopala Swami Iyengar, K. M. Munshi, Muhammad Sadullah, B. L. Mitter, and D. P. Khetan were members of the drafting committee. However, B. L. Mitter resigned, and D. P. Khetan passed away, leading to changes in the committee's composition. N. Madhavarao and T. T. Krishnamachari became members after their departures.",
      "arr": ["1,2,3", "2, 3,4", "1, 3", "2,4"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who chaired the Fundamental Rights and Minority Committee?",
      "answer": "Sardar Patel",
      "moreDetails": "The Fundamental Rights and Minority Committee was an essential committee formed during the constitution-making process",
      "arr": [
        "Sardar Patel",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "H. C. Mukherjee",
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the Chairman of the Fundamental Rights Sub-Committee?",
      "answer": "J. B. Kripalani",
      "moreDetails": "Played a crucial role in discussing and framing the fundamental rights in the Indian Constitution",
      "arr": [
        "Sardar Patel",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "H. C. Mukherjee",
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the Chairman of the Minority Sub-Committee?",
      "answer": "H. C. Mukherjee",
      "moreDetails": "Responsible for addressing the rights and protection of minorities in the Indian Constitution",
      "arr": [
        "Sardar Patel",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "H. C. Mukherjee",
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the Chairman of the Flag Committee?",
      "answer": "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
      "moreDetails": "The Flag Committee was tasked with deciding on the national flag of India. Dr. Rajendra Prasad, who later became the first President of India, chaired the committee.",
      "arr": [
        "Sardar Patel",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "H. C. Mukherjee",
        "Dr. Rajendra Prasad"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following presided over the House Committee?",
      "answer": "Pattabhi Sitaramaiah",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "Pattabhi Sitaramaiah",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Motturi Satyanarayana",
        "B. R. Ambedkar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following chaired the Language Committee?",
      "answer": "Motturi Satyanarayana",
      "moreDetails": "Responsible for deciding on the language policies in the Indian Constitution, including the official languages",
      "arr": [
        "Pattabhi Sitaramaiah",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Motturi Satyanarayana",
        "B. R. Ambedkar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who presided over the Union Power Committee and the Union Constitution Committee in the Constitution-Making Committee?",
      "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "Pattabhi Sitaramaiah",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Motturi Satyanarayana",
        "B. R. Ambedkar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the chairman of the State Committee in the Constitution-Making Committee?",
      "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "Pattabhi Sitaramaiah",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Motturi Satyanarayana",
        "B. R. Ambedkar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the chairman of the Provincial Constitution Committee?",
      "answer": "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
        "Rajendra Prasad",
        "K. M. Munshi",
        "Pattabhi Sitaramaiah"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who chaired the Rules and Procedure Committee and Steering Committee in the Constitution-Making Committee?",
      "answer": "Rajendra Prasad",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
        "Rajendra Prasad",
        "K. M. Munshi",
        "Pattabhi Sitaramaiah"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which committee in the Constitution-Making Committee is known as the 'Committee of Committees'?",
      "answer": "Drafting Committee",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "House Committee",
        "Drafting Committee",
        "Union Power Committee",
        "Union Constitution Committee"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who acted as the Legal Adviser to the Constitution Drafting Committee?",
      "answer": "B. N. Rao",
      "moreDetails": "* B.N Rao was the first Indian to become a judge at the International Court of Justice.\n* B N Rao's brother Benegal Rama Rao was the longest serving Reserve Bank Governor.",
      "arr": [
        "Benegal Ramrao",
        "H. C. Mukherjee",
        "J. B. Kripalani",
        "B. N. Rao"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Parsis were represented in the Constitution Drafting Committee by which of the following?",
      "answer": "H. P. Modi",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["D. P. Khetan", "H. P. Modi", "Frank Anthony", "H. C. Mukherjee"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who represented the Anglo-Indian section in the Constitution-Making Committee?",
      "answer": "Frank Anthony",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["D. P. Khetan", "H. P. Modi", "Frank Anthony", "H. C. Mukherjee"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who represented the minorities in the Constituent Assembly?",
      "answer": "H. C. Mukherjee",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["D. P. Khetan", "H. P. Modi", "Frank Anthony", "H. C. Mukherjee"]
    },
    {
      "question": "How many women members were there in the Constituent Assembly?\n",
      "answer": 15,
      "moreDetails": "Sarojini Naidu, Vijayalakshmi Pandit, Durgabhai Deshmukh, Begum Isaaz Rasool, Rajkumari Amrita Kaul, Hansa Mehta, Sucheta Kripalani, Renuka Rai, Leela Rai, Kamala Chaudhary, Malathi Chaudhary, and Purnima Banerjee were women who were members of the Constituent Assembly. Additionally, three other Malayalam women were also in the Constitution Making Committee.",
      "arr": [15, 14, 13, 11]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following women was a member of the Constitution Making Committee?\n\n",
      "answer": "All of them",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "Rajkumari Amrita Kaul",
        "Sarojini Naidu",
        "Begum Aizaz Rasool",
        "All of them"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following was a Malayali woman who was a member of the Constitution Making Committee of India?\n1) Animascreen\n2) Dakshayani Velayudhan\n3) Lakshmi. N. Menon\n4) Ammu Swaminathan",
      "answer": "1,2 and 4",
      "moreDetails": "There were three Malayali women who were members of the Constitution Making Committee.",
      "arr": ["1,2,3 and 4", "1,2 and 3", "1,2 and 4", "2,3 and 4"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the only Dalit woman to be a member of the Constitution Drafting Committee?",
      "answer": "Dakshayani Velayudhan",
      "moreDetails": "Dakshayani Velayudhan was the youngest woman member of the Constitution Drafting Committee. Begum Aizaz Rasool was the only Muslim woman in the committee.",
      "arr": [
        "Ammu Swaminathan",
        "Kamala Chowdhury",
        "Purnima Banerjee",
        "Dakshayani Velayudhan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was a member of the Constitution-Making Committee and later became the first woman governor of India?",
      "answer": "Sarojini Naidu",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "Vijayalakshmi Pandit",
        "Sarojini Naidu",
        "Sucheta Kripalani",
        "Rajkumari Amrita Kaul"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which woman, a member of the Constitution Drafting Committee, later became India's first woman Chief Minister?",
      "answer": "C) Sucheta Kripalani",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) Vijayalakshmi Pandit",
        "B) Sarojini Naidu",
        "C) Sucheta Kripalani",
        "D) Rajkumari Amrita Kaul"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which woman, who was a member of the Constitution-Making Committee, later became an ambassador?",
      "answer": "A) Vijayalakshmi Pandit",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) Vijayalakshmi Pandit",
        "B) Sarojini Naidu",
        "C) Sucheta Kripalani",
        "D) Rajkumari Amrita Kaul"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the first woman to become a Union Cabinet Minister and was also a member of the Constitution Drafting Committee?",
      "answer": "D) Rajkumari Amrita Kaul",
      "moreDetails": "Rajkumari Amrita Kaul, who was a member of the Constitution Drafting Committee, later became the Union Minister of Health and founded the All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS) in Delhi.",
      "arr": [
        "A) Vijayalakshmi Pandit",
        "B) Sarojini Naidu",
        "C) Sucheta Kripalani",
        "D) Rajkumari Amrita Kaul"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When did the Drafting Committee first submit the draft of the Constitution to the Constitution-Making Committee?",
      "answer": "B) February 21, 1948",
      "moreDetails": "Dr. B. R. Ambedkar submitted the first draft of the Constitution to the Constituent Assembly on February 21, 1948, after making changes to the draft prepared by B. N. Rao, the legal advisor to the Constituent Assembly. The final draft was placed before the Constitution-Making Committee on November 4, 1948.",
      "arr": [
        "A) February 21, 1947",
        "B) February 21, 1948",
        "C) November 4, 1947",
        "D) November 4, 1948"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When was the Constitution of India adopted by the Constitution-Making Committee?",
      "answer": "B) November 26, 1949",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) January 26, 1950",
        "B) November 26, 1949",
        "C) November 4, 1948",
        "D) November 15, 1948"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When did the Constitution of India come into effect?",
      "answer": "A) January 26, 1950",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) January 26, 1950",
        "B) November 26, 1949",
        "C) November 4, 1948",
        "D) November 15, 1948"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "India is a republic because of:",
      "answer": "D) The head of government of India is elected by the people.",
      "moreDetails": "The head of government in India is the President. Although the President is not directly elected by the people, they are elected by the people's representatives.",
      "arr": [
        "A) There is a constitution",
        "B) There is the President",
        "C) It is a federal country",
        "D) The head of government of India is elected by the people."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "What was the time required by the Constitution-Making Committee to finalize the Constitution of India?",
      "answer": "A) 2 years 11 months 17 days",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) 2 years 11 months 17 days",
        "B) 2 years 8 months 11 days",
        "C) 2 years 10 months 12 days",
        "D) 2 years 6 months 18 days"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "How many times did the Constitution-Making Committee meet to finalize the Constitution of India?",
      "answer": "A) 165 days in 11 sessions",
      "moreDetails": "The Constitution was finalized by the Constitution-Making Committee on November 26, 1949, in 11 meetings. The last meeting of the Committee was on January 24, 1950.",
      "arr": [
        "A) 165 days in 11 sessions",
        "B) 180 days in 12 sessions",
        "C) 165 days in 10 sessions",
        "D) 165 days in 9 sessions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "How many members signed the Constitution of India at the last meeting of the Constitution-Making Committee on January 24, 1950?",
      "answer": "D) 284",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["A) 389", "B) 299", "C) 207", "D) 284"]
    },
    {
      "question": "National Law Day/Constitution Day of India is observed on:",
      "answer": "A) November 26",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) November 26",
        "B) December 6",
        "C) December 9",
        "D) January 26"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The reason for choosing January 26 as the date when the Constitution came into force:",
      "answer": "B) Because it was the day celebrated as India's Independence Day before independence",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) B. N. Rao's birthday",
        "B) Because it was the day celebrated as India's Independence Day before independence",
        "C) To commemorate Mahatma Gandhi's return from South Africa",
        "D) For the convenience of Lord Mountbatten"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When the Constitution of India came into force, it stated:",
      "answer": "C) 395 Sections, 22 Parts, 8 Tables",
      "moreDetails": "The Constitution of India currently has 470 Articles, 25 Parts, and 12 Schedules. Articles 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 60, 324, 366, 367, 379, 380, 388, 391, 392, and 393 had retrospective effect.\r\n\r\n",
      "arr": [
        "A) 395 Sections, 8 Parts, 12 Tables",
        "B) 395 Sections, 12 Parts, 8 Tables",
        "C) 395 Sections, 22 Parts, 8 Tables",
        "D) 396 Sections, 8 Parts, 12 Tables"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which animal is found on the official seal of the Constitution-Making Committee of India?",
      "answer": "A) Elephant",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["A) Elephant", "B) Bull", "C) Lion", "D) Tiger"]
    },
    {
      "question": "The constitution makers adopted ideas from the constitutions of how many countries to frame the Indian Constitution?",
      "answer": "D) 10",
      "moreDetails": "The constitution makers examined the constitutions of 60 countries and incorporated ideas from 10 countries. The Indian Constitution is most influenced by the British Constitution.",
      "arr": ["A) 60", "B) 50", "C) 30", "D) 10"]
    },
    {
      "question": "How much did the Constituent Assembly spend to complete the Constitution of India?",
      "answer": "C) 64 lakhs",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["A) 1.26 crores", "B) 1.01 crores", "C) 64 lakhs", "D) 30 lakhs"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which illustrator designed the cover page of the Indian Constitution?",
      "answer": "C) Nandalal Bose",
      "moreDetails": "Nandalal Bose is also known as the father of modern Indian painting. Illustrator Ram Manohar Sinha designed the Preamble Page of the Constitution of India. Deenath Bhargava is the artist who created the pencil sketch of India's national symbol, the Lion Mudra.",
      "arr": [
        "A) Deenath Bhargava",
        "B) Satyendra Nath Tagore",
        "C) Nandalal Bose",
        "D) Ram Manohar Sinha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The manuscript of the Indian Constitution was prepared by?",
      "answer": "C) Prem Bihari Naren Raizada",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) Nandalal Bose",
        "B) Deenath Bhargava",
        "C) Prem Bihari Naren Raizada",
        "D) Ram Manohar Sinha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When did the Constituent Assembly accept Hindi as the official language of India?",
      "answer": "B) September 14, 1949",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) September 14, 1947",
        "B) September 14, 1949",
        "C) September 14, 1948",
        "D) September 1950"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
      "answer": "D) All of these",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) The National Flag was adopted by the Constituent Assembly on 22 July 1947.",
        "B) The National Anthem was adopted by the Constituent Assembly on 24 January 1950.",
        "C) The National Song was adopted by the Constituent Assembly on 24 January 1950.",
        "D) All of these"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In which of the following is the concept borrowed from the British Constitution to the Indian Constitution?\n1) Legislation and Citizenship.\r\n2) Parliamentary System and Rule of Law.\r\n3) General Election and Election Commission.\r\n4) First-past-the-post system.",
      "answer": "D) All of these",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) 1, 2 only",
        "B) 2, 3 only",
        "C) 1, 2, 3 only",
        "D) All of these"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following concepts is borrowed from the Canadian Constitution to the Indian Constitution?\n1) Residual Powers\n2) Semi-federal System\n3)Position and Duties of the Speaker\n4)Title and Duties of the Governor",
      "answer": "D) 1, 2, 4",
      "moreDetails": "Note: Concepts such as the Speaker, Attorney General, Auditor General, and Election Commissioner are borrowed from Britain.",
      "arr": ["A) 1, 2 only", "B) 1, 2, 3 only", "C) 2, 3 only", "D) 1, 2, 4"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following concepts is borrowed from the Irish Constitution to the Indian Constitution?\n1) Presidential election model\r\n2) Model of the President as the head of administration\r\n3) Directive Principles of State Policy\r\n4) Nominating Members of Rajya Sabha",
      "answer": "A) 1, 3, 4 only",
      "moreDetails": "The Presidential Head of State model was adopted from the USA, while the Presidential Head of Administration model was adopted from the British Constitution.",
      "arr": [
        "A) 1, 3, 4 only",
        "B) 1, 2, 3 only",
        "C) 3, 4 only",
        "D) All of these"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Arrange the following concepts correctly in the order of the countries from which the Indian Constitution borrows them.\n1) Emergency\n2) Concurrent List\n3) Constitutional Amendment\n4) Concept of Republic\na) France\r\nb) South Africa\r\nc) Australia\r\nd) Germany",
      "answer": "D) 1d, 2c, 3b, 4a",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": [
        "A) 1b, 2a, 3d, 4c",
        "B) 1d, 2a, 3b, 4c",
        "C) 1a, 2d, 3b, 4c",
        "D) 1d, 2c, 3b, 4a"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the concept of 'procedure established by law'?",
      "answer": "C) Japan",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["A) South Africa", "B) France", "C) Japan", "D) Russia"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which country inspired the system of election for Rajya Sabha members?",
      "answer": "A) South Africa",
      "moreDetails": "The concept of nominated members for the Rajya Sabha has been adopted from Ireland.",
      "arr": ["A) South Africa", "B) Ireland", "C) Germany", "D) Britain"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is borrowed from the U.S. Constitution?\n1) Independent Judiciary\r\n2) Judicial Review\r\n3) Fundamental Duties\r\n4) Impeachment Procedure",
      "answer": "C) 1, 2, 4 only",
      "moreDetails": "Fundamental Duties are borrowed from the USSR. However, the U.S. Constitution influenced the Indian Constitution with concepts like Fundamental Rights, the Preamble model, and the structure of the Supreme Court.",
      "arr": [
        "A) 1, 2 only",
        "B) 2, 3, 4 only",
        "C) 1, 2, 4 only",
        "D) All of these"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which country's constitution influenced the laws in the Indian Constitution related to internal trade and commerce?",
      "answer": "C) Australia",
      "moreDetails": "",
      "arr": ["A) France", "B) Canada", "C) Australia", "D) Japan"]
    }
  ]
}
